# 哈喽大家好
Hello everyone
# 打个招呼宝贝
Say ‘hello’, my sweetheart
# 你说哈喽大家好你是谁
Tell them who you are
# 哈喽大家好我是沺沺
Hello everyone, I’m Tian Tian
# 嗯沺沺
Good job, Tian Tian
# 出生第一天
On the day of birth
# 三个月
Three months old
# 十一个月
Eleven months old
# 一岁
One year old
# 三岁半
Three and a half years old
# 四岁
Four years old
# 四岁半
Four and a half years old
# 五岁
Five years old
# 哈喽 大家好
Hello everyone
# 今天又请个假做一个我女儿喜欢吃的几个菜
I took another leave today to cook some of my daughter’s favourite dishes
# 这个是什么宝贝
What’s this, my sweetheart?
# 多宝鱼
It’s turbot
# 是什么多宝鱼
How shall I cook it?
# 你最喜欢怎么做这个
What’s your favourite version of turbot?
# 我最喜欢弄番茄酱做
My favourite is the one made with ketchup
# 番茄酱做 你说的是那个吧
Made with ketchup? You are talking about…
# 那个松鼠鱼对不对
The squirrel fish, right?
# 这个我们做多宝鱼 清蒸多宝鱼
But this is turbot, and we will steam it
# 今天我们做一个清汤牛肉丸
Today, we will make beef meatball bouillon
# 然后做一个清蒸多宝鱼 还有一个姜葱花甲
Steamed turbot, stir-fried clams with ginger and spring onion
# 然后再炒一些孩子比较喜欢吃的素菜
And some sautéed vegetables that my daughter loves to eat
# 今天是我女儿满5岁的生日
Today is my daughter’s 5th birthday
# 所以请个假 简简单单的做一个菜 做来今天中午吃
So I took the leave and I’m going to cook some simple dishes for lunch
# 我先切碎 沺沺等一下要不要来试一下
I’m mincing the beef first. Do you want to have a try later, Tian Tian?
# 要
Yes
# 算了吧
No, you don’t
# 你也来试 你敢切吗 那个刀很利的哦
Are you brave enough to have a try? That knife is very sharp
# 你不是跟爸爸说你长大了要当厨师吗
Haven’t you told dad that you want to be a chef when you grow up?
# 是不是
Yes?
# 是
Yes
# 那等你长大了我教你好不好
Then I will teach you how to use the knife once you grow up, deal?
# 好
Deal
# 我们站到这里看好不好
Shall we stand here and watch?
# 不要 葱妈妈也会伤心的
No, the ‘mom spring onion’ will be sad
# 还有葱妈妈
There is a ‘mom spring onion’?
# 你的意思是爸爸切了葱 葱妈妈要伤心是吗
You mean that the ‘mom spring onion’ will be sad if dad chops it?
# 不是 葱宝宝这个是
No, this is the ‘baby spring onion’
# 哦 这个是葱宝宝
Ok, this is the ‘baby spring onion’
# 嗯
Correct
# 爸爸 这是姜妈妈
Dad, this is the ‘mom ginger’
# 嗯 我会切得它很舒服的 它不会感到痛苦
Alright, I will make it comfortable and it won’t feel any pain when I cut it
# 这是多宝鱼宝宝 它也会伤心的
This is the ‘baby turbot’, and it will also be sad
# 沺沺 过来吃饭了 来
Come and eat lunch, Tian Tian
# 吃什么 沺沺
What do you want to eat, Tian Tian?
# 多宝鱼
Turbot
# 多宝鱼是不 爸爸给你弄
Good choice. Let dad grab some for you
# 吃撒吃撒
Help yourselves, guys
# 吃嘛
Sure
# 这个好吃噶
It tastes delicious
# 原先腥的你吃不来噶
You are not used to eating fish with strong flavour
# 沺沺 你知道你今天多少岁了吗
Tian Tian, do you know how old you are today?
# 知道
Of course
# 你今天几岁
How old are you?
# 5岁
Five
# 5岁啊
Five years old
# 5岁了是不是都长大了
Are you a grown-up now at five?
# 嗯
Yes
# 长大了还要不要吃糖
Do you still want to eat candies if you are a grown-up?
# 你说长大了不吃糖了
Tell him that you won’t candies because you’ve grown up
# 以后还要不要吃糖
Do you still want to eat candies in the future?
# 少吃糖
Eat less maybe
# 要少吃点
Yes, eat less
# 说她吃糖她心头不高兴
She’s not happy when we’re accusing her of eating candies
# 等下给你切蛋糕好不好
I will serve you the birthday cake in a minute, alright?
# 好
Alright
# 要不要吃
Do you want to eat the cake?
# 要
Yes
# 沺沺祝你生日快乐 宝贝
Happy birthday to you, Tian Tian, my sweetheart
# 谢谢爸爸
Thanks, dad
# 沺沺生日快乐哦
Happy birthday, Tian Tian
# 祝你生日快乐 沺沺
Happy birthday to you, Tian Tian
# 谢谢奶奶啊
Say ‘thank you, grandma’
# 谢谢
Thank you
# 多吃点哦沺沺
Have some more, Tian Tian
# 好
Ok
# 菜籽是什么
What’s rapeseed?
# 菜籽就是我们炒菜会用到的菜籽油
Rapeseed is used to make the rapeseed oil we use for cooking
# 因为爸爸是厨师
As dad is a chef
# 你喜不喜欢爸爸做的菜
Do you like the dishes dad cooks?
# 喜欢 爸爸有100个香
Yes, dad can make 100 kinds of aroma
# 哦 炒的菜有100个香啊
Oh, my dishes have 100 kinds of aroma?
# 嗯
Yes
# 等爸爸妈妈老了我就会洗碗还会炒菜
I will do the dishes and cook for you when mom and dad become old
# 哦 真棒
That’s fantastic, sweetheart